JACKSON SHEPPARD

Santa Barbara, CA, 93101

Phone: 650-862-9401 | Email: jackson.sheppard@gmail.com

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/jsheppard95/ | GitHub: https://github.com/jsheppard95/ |

Portfolio: https://jsheppard95.github.io/JacksonSheppard_Portfolio/

DATA ANALYST

SUMMARY

Data analyst with a Bachelor of Science in physics (with honors). Two years experience in a collaborative software development environment as a controls engineer at SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory earning the SLAC Spot Award for Dependability. Certificate in data analytics and skills including Python, SQL, MongoDB, JavaScript/HTML, and PLC programming. Highly organized with experience balancing multiple responsibilities and a dedicated learner with a passion for problem solving. Quantitative analysis experience in a variety of technical environments and excellent written/oral communication skills to express ideas and learn from others.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: Python, C++, SQL, JavaScript ES6+, HTML5, R, MATLAB, Experimental Physics and Industrial Control System (EPICS), PLC

Applications: NumPy, pandas, Matplotlib, hvPlot, Flask, PySpark, SQLAlchemy/SQLite, scikit-learn, imbalanced-learn, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, AWS RDS, AWS S3, D3.js, Plotly, Leaflet, GeoJSON, Bootstrap, Tidyverse, EPICS Display Manager, Tc2 MC2

Tools: Jupyter Notebook, Google Colaboratory, Excel/VBA, Tableau, Beckhoff, Visual Molecular Dynamics, Visual

Studio Code, Git/GitHub, SVN

Concepts: ETL, Data Visualization, Big Data, NLP, Machine Learning, Linux

PROJECTS

Mapping Earthquakes | https://github.com/jsheppard95/Mapping Earthquakes

Web application with interactive maps of cities, airports, airline routes, and earthquakes from local JSON/JavaScript files and API calls to USGS GeoJSON sources.

• Role: Sole author

• Tools: JavaScript, Leaflet, D3.js, Mapbox, Python

Mission-to-Mars | https://github.com/jsheppard95/Mission-to-Mars

Interactive web scraping application acquiring Mars data, storing using MongoDB, and then visualizing in a Flask application.

• Role: Sole author

• Tools: Python, Splinter, bs4, Pandas, Flask, MongoDB, Jupyter Notebook

lcls-plc-lfe-optics | https://github.com/pcdshub/lcls-plc-lfe-optics

PLC project and EPICS Input/Output Controller (IOC) for deployed LCLS optics MR1L0 and MR2L0 relying on lcls-twincat-optics library.

- Role: Defined motion axes for MR1L0 and MR2L0 optics and performed system checkouts to verify motion requirements.
- Tools: PLC, Beckhoff, Tc2 MC2, pytmc, EPICS

EXPERIENCE

Controls Engineer

SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory

November 2020 - Present Menlo Park, CA

Part-time position in the Experiment Control Systems Delivery (ECS, formerly PCDS) group within the Linac Coherent Light Source (LCLS) while attending the UC Berkeley Extension Data Analytics Boot Camp. Responsible for remote support of LCLS-II style Beckhoff motion control systems.

Key Accomplishments:

• Created procedures for setup, basic operation, and troubleshooting of motion control systems under expertise.

- Coordinated installation and checkout of motion controls for CVMI interaction point at the TMO endstation.
- Trained recent hires and colleagues on systems under expertise to create a more uniform understanding within the group.

Science and Engineering Associate SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory

September 2018 - November 2020

Menlo Park, CA

Controls engineer in the Experiment Control Systems (ECS) Delivery group within the Linac Coherent Light Source (LCLS). During active operations, responsible for experiment setup and on-call technical support of assigned experiments at assigned instruments. Over instrument downtime, responsible for integration of new LCLS-II devices into ECS-developed control systems.

Key Accomplishments:

- Integrated motors, cameras, temperature sensors, timing trigger signals, and other user devices into the ECS-developed controls software stack for assigned experiments.
- Expanded device support through Python development on a Linux system (IPython sessions containing device objects for specific experiments).
- Deployed a controls upgrade to existing Offset Mirror System to employ LCLS-II style Beckhoff motion hardware and PLC software interface. Coordinated system reinstallation and performed checkout to ensure motion requirements were satisfied. Integrated system into ECS controls stack for use by scientists during experiments.
- Received SLAC Spot Award for Dependability (August 4, 2020).

Summer Student

June 2018 - September 2018

SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory

Menlo Park, CA

Student under the mentorship of staff physicist Claudio Pellegrini. Worked on free electron laser (FEL) beam dynamics simulations using GENESIS and MATLAB for preprocessing and analysis.

- Key Accomplishments:
 - Characterized the undulator "taper profile" by finding the optimal relationship for magnetic field strength as a function of longitudinal distance using simulations and iterative search methods.
 - Presented findings in the LCLS Summer Internship Poster Session with other students, mentors, and SLAC faculty (Received LCLS Poster Award, 2nd place).
 - Published findings in the Journal of Synchrotron Radiation: Halavanau, A., Decker, F. J., Emma, C., Sheppard, J., Pellegrini, C. 2019. Very high brightness and power LCLS-II hard X-ray pulses. *J. Synchrotron Rad.* **26(3)**:635-646.

Undergraduate Research Assistant

January 2018 - June 2018

University of California, Santa Barbara

Santa Barbara, CA

Student in the Shea Group within the Department of Chemistry at UCSB. Participated in computational research that applied statistical and data science techniques to molecular dynamics simulations in order to model complex biological processes.

Key Accomplishments:

- Cleaned and pre-processed data using NumPy and employed cluster analysis techniques using Python to prepare data for models built with TensorFlow and Keras.
- Produced latent space visualization with Matplotlib.
- Utilized 3D modeling software Visual Molecular Dynamics to visualize protein folding.
- Earned Department of Physics Academic Honors (May 13, 2018).

EDUCATION

Data Analytics Certificate: UC Berkeley Extension, Berkeley, CA

Expected May 2021

A 24-week intensive program focused on gaining technical programming skills in Excel, VBA, Python, R, JavaScript, SQL Databases, Tableau, Big Data, and Machine Learning.

Bachelor of Science, Physics: University of California, Santa Barbara, Santa Barbara, CA

June 2018

GPA: 3.79 (High Honors)